# Bharathkumar "Tiny" Ramachandra

tnybny@gmail.com | +1 (437) 255-2545 | United States | Personal homepage

### **SUMMARY**

Researcher in computer vision and deep learning and leader of high-performing ML teams. Expertise in judging, choosing and creating successful prototypes of deep learning systems based on recent academic advances, and in growing and leading cross-cultural teams with empathy. A lifelong learner with an obsession for improvement.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

### Senior Research Scientist at Geopipe Inc.

### Aug 2022 - present

Backend development of deep learning models to build 3D models of cities from aerial imagery.

### Lead Machine Learning Scientist at Invision Al

### Aug 2021 - Aug 2022

- Grew, led and retained a team of 4 machine learning scientists and engineers.
- Led initiatives such as federated learning, knowledge distillation and multitask loss balancing for object detection.
- Identified key strategic opportunities for the use of machine learning in our products and directed development of these features to build out new technological capabilities.
- Collaborated actively with peer engineering, product, deployment and front-end development teams.

### Computer Vision Scientist at Wrnch Inc. (acq. Hinge Health)

### Mar 2020 - Aug 2021

- Developed a novel system to solve a problem that the team had been grappling with for the past 5 years a fully differentiable bottom-up joint-to-person association method for multi-person pose estimation with a Transformer network.
- Spearheaded the development of a novel system for 3D human pose estimation from a single RGB image.
- Contributed towards critical strategy to several projects on deep generative modeling of images with GANs, 3D hand pose
  estimation, 2D human pose estimation and inverse kinematics.

### Computer Vision Research Intern at Mitsubishi Electric Research Labs

# Summers 2018, 2019 | with Michael Jones

- Developed a new benchmark dataset, evaluation protocol and baseline algorithms for video anomaly detection that has nudged research in a more meaningful direction.
- Developed a novel video anomaly detection algorithm that learns a metric with a Siamese CNN from source datasets and
  uses it to subsequently score video patches in a target dataset.
- Generalized the Siamese CNN approach to process data across multiple scales using region proposals, Spatial Pyramid Pooling and a margin-based metric loss.

### **Data Science Intern at Samsung Research America**

# Summer 2017 | with Rui Chen

• Built a logistic regression pipeline on Spark to predict attributes of users based on historical transaction information.

# **EDUCATION**

# Ph.D. in Computer Science | 2014 - 2019 | GPA 4.0

### North Carolina State University | with Ranga Raju Vatsavai

- Dissertation on 'Anomaly Detection in Videos'.
- Wrote the most comprehensive survey on Video Anomaly Detection to-date.
- Reproduced code for papers that proposed convolutional auto-encoders to perform video anomaly detection using TensorFlow. 50+ ★s, 15+ forks on GitHub
- Collaborated in projects on video action recognition, semi-supervised image classification, remote sensing change detection, multi-modal image classification and manifold estimation.
- Relevant coursework: Visual Sensing, Advanced Machine Learning, Spatial and Temporal Data Mining, Artificial Intelligence,
   Data Science, Advanced Spatial Statistics, Design and Analysis of Algorithms.

# B.E. (Hons.) in Computer Science | 2010 - 2014 | GPA: 3.51

Birla Institute of Technology and Science - Pilani, Dubai

## OTHER PROJECTS (GITHUB)

Implemented a manifold-aware density estimator using Python called Manifold Parzen Windows.

- Augmented a sparse point-cloud mapping library, ORB-SLAM2, to perform real-time SLAM using thermal sensors for energy audits of buildings.
- Performed highly optimized large-scale distributed training of deep neural networks and classification of satellite imagery on the latest Intel Xeon CPUs.
- Data Crunch for Social Good Event, NCData4Good: mapped food banks with their accessibility by public transport to identify food deserts in counties in North Carolina.

### **TECHNICAL PROFICIENCY**

Python; PyTorch; TensorFlow; OpenCV; Scikit-learn.

Deep learning; Computer Vision; Machine Learning; Artificial Intelligence.

# **SERVICE**

- Program Chair: SSTDM workshop at ICDM '21.
- Program Committee: SSTDM '19 (at ICDM '19).
- Reviewer: SIGSPATIAL ['22], CIKM ['21, '20], TPAMI ['20], WACV ['23, '22, '21, '20], ICDM ['19], KDD['18], PKDD ['19], AAAI ['20, '19], SDM ['20, '19, '18], PAKDD ['18], SSTD ['17], SSTDM ['16, '17].

### **TALKS**

- "Innovation to Implementation: Building Deep Tech Powered Systems" at McGill Al Society's Learnathon Feb 2021.
- "Understanding Human Pose" at McGill Al Society's Hackathon Sep 2020.

# **A**WARDS

- The Peak's 2022 Emerging Leaders in Artificial Intelligence
- WACV 2020 PhD consortium + travel award.
- Best paper award at ICCS 2016.

### **PATENTS**

• "Pose Parsing using a Transformer Network" - provisional patent 2021.

### SELECT PUBLICATIONS (GOOGLE SCHOLAR)

- Ramachandra, B., Jones, M., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2020). A Survey of Single-Scene Video Anomaly Detection. IEEE
   Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence.
- Ramachandra, B., & Jones, M. (2020). Street Scene: A new dataset and evaluation protocol for video anomaly detection. In The IEEE Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (pp. 2569-2578).
- Ramachandra, B., Jones, M., & Vatsavai, R. (2020). Learning a distance function with a Siamese network to localize
  anomalies in videos. In *The IEEE Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision* (pp. 2598-2607).
- Ramachandra, B., Jones, M., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2021). Perceptual metric learning for video anomaly detection. Machine Vision and Applications, 32(3), 1-17.
- Gadiraju, K. K., Ramachandra, B., Chen, Z., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2020, August). Multimodal Deep Learning Based Crop
  Classification Using Multispectral and Multitemporal Satellite Imagery. In Proceedings of the 26th ACM SIGKDD International
  Conference on Knowledge Discovery & Data Mining (pp. 3234-3242).
- Chen, Z., Dutton, B., Ramachandra, B., Wu, T., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2020). Local Clustering with Mean Teacher for Semi-supervised Learning. To appear in IEEE International Conference on Pattern Recognition 2020.
- Ramachandra, B., Dutton, B., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2019). Anomalous cluster detection in spatiotemporal meteorological fields. Statistical Analysis and Data Mining: The ASA Data Science Journal, 12(2), 88-100.
- Ramachandra, B., Gadiraju, K. K., Vatsavai, R. R., Kaiser, D. P., & Karnowski, T. P. (2016). Detecting extreme events in gridded climate data. *Procedia Computer Science*, *80*, 2397-2401. (Best Paper Award)
- Gadiraju, K. K., Ramachandra, B., Shashidharan, A., Dutton, B., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2019, December). Scalable Data Parallel Approaches to Anomaly Detection in Climate Data using Gaussian Processes. In 2019 18th IEEE International Conference On Machine Learning And Applications (ICMLA) (pp. 485-488). IEEE.
- Chen, Z., Ramachandra, B., Wu, T., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2018). Relational Long Short-Term Memory for Video Action Recognition. arXiv preprint arXiv:1811.07059.
- Chen, Z., Ramachandra, B., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2020). Consistency Regularization with Generative Adversarial Networks for Semi-Supervised Image Classification. arXiv preprint arXiv:2007.03844.
- Ramachandra, B., Dutton, B., & Vatsavai, R. R. (2019). Estimating a Manifold from a Tangent Bundle Learner. arXiv preprint arXiv:1906.07661.